<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Armies declaration examined and compared with their declaration May 6. Their petition and addresse May 12. And their petition and representation. Discovering some of their contradictions, lies, calumnies, hypocrisie, and designes. Well worthy observation.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 92 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75592</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3713</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1006_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207901</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866920</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866920</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119208</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75592)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119208)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 149:E1006[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Armies declaration examined and compared with their declaration May 6. Their petition and addresse May 12. And their petition and representation. Discovering some of their contradictions, lies, calumnies, hypocrisie, and designes. Well worthy observation.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed, 1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: A declaration of the General Council of the Officers of the Army: agreed upon at Wallingford-house, 27th Octob. 1659.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf bears a postscript.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "9ber [i.e. September] 8".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119208:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ARMIES DECLARATION Examined and Compared WITH Their <hi>DECLARATION</hi> May 6. Their <hi>PETITION</hi> and <hi>ADDRESSE</hi> May 12. AND Their <hi>PETITION</hi> and <hi>REPRESENTATION.</hi> Diſcovering ſome of their Contradictions, Lies, Calumnies, Hypocriſie, and Deſignes. Well worthy Obſervation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:119208:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119208:2"/>
            <head>THE ARMIES DECLARATION <hi>EXAMINED,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>IT was the ſerious wiſh of ſome who were very careful for the <hi>reputation of the Army,</hi> after they underſtood how well the Army had made good their moſt <hi>Chriſtian Declaration of the Sixth of</hi> May <hi>paſt,</hi> by forcing the Parliament a <hi>ſecond time,</hi> according to their wonted way of Expoſition or doing clean contrary, that now they would no more declare, to make themſelves and friends, the ſcorne of Heathens for falſneſs and ficklenſs, but leave themſelves a ſufficient latitude and field to ramble in, who could never yet be kept within the limits they had ſet out for themſelves; however they have pleaſed me better as it fals out, for without peradventure many men who but the other day excuſed, extenuated (or at leaſt reſpited their judgement upon) the ſtrange practice of the Army in keeping out the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, deamed that thoſe worthy Perſons had <hi>miſerably violated their truſt,</hi> or had <hi>practiſed ſome unheard of miſchief againſt the good people of this Nation, that ſhould neceſſitate this extravagant, and indirect proceeding of the Army,</hi> contrary to their <hi>own Declaration</hi> of a very late date, and all <hi>Humanity</hi> and <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> who by reading this <hi>New Declaration,</hi> or at leaſt by taking the Examination thereof along with me, muſt needs be undeceived by little and little, till they underſtand
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119208:3"/> the naked reaſon of theſe <hi>Maſters of miſrule;</hi> wherein, the better to help thy obſervation, take here verbatim their Declaration of <hi>May</hi> Sixth, which will take up but little room, which I re-print, that you may ſee I mean to deal fairly, and it will be of ſome uſe in the ſequel. It begins thus:</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="declaration">
               <body>
                  <p>THE Publique concernments of this Common-wealth being through a Viciſſitude of dangers, deliverances and backſlidings of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> brought into that ſtate and poſture wherein they now ſtand, and our ſelves alſo contributing thereunto, by wandering divers wayes, from righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and equal paths; and although there hath been many eſſaies to obviate the dangers, and to ſettle theſe Nations in Peace and Proſperity, yet all have proved ineffectual, the only wiſe God in the courſe of his providence diſappointing all endeavours therein.</p>
                  <p>And alſo obſerving, to our great grief, that the good Spirit which formerly appeared amongſt us; in the carrying on of this great work, did daily decline, ſo as the Good old Cauſe it ſelf became a reproach; We have been led to look back, and examine the cauſe of the Lords withdrawing his wonted preſence from us, and where we turned out of the way, that through mercy we might return and give him the glory.</p>
                  <p>And amongſt other things, calling to minde, that the long Parliament conſiſting of the members which continued there ſitting untill the <hi>20th.</hi> of <hi>April 1653.</hi> were eminent Aſſertors of that Cauſe, and had a ſpecial pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God with them, and were ſignally bleſſed in that work (the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of many good people concurring with ours therein) we judge it our duty to invite the aforeſaid Members to return to the exerciſe and diſcharge of their truſt, as before the ſaid <hi>20th.</hi> of <hi>April 1653.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And therefore we do hereby moſt earneſtly deſire the Parliament, conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thoſe Members who continued to ſit ſince the year <hi>1648,</hi> untill the <hi>20th.</hi> of <hi>April. 1653.</hi> to return to the exerciſe and diſcharge of their Truſt, and we ſhall be ready in our places, to yeeld them, as becomes us, our utmoſt Aſſiſtance to ſit in ſafety; for the improving the preſent opportunity for ſetling and ſecuring the Peace and Freedom of this Common-wealth: praying for the preſence and bleſſing of God upon their endeavours.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Signed by direction of the Lord <hi>Fleetwood</hi> and the Council of Officers of the Army. <hi>Tho. Sandford</hi> Secret.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>6. May 1659.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119208:3"/>
            <p>I ſhall trouble your Memory but little to look further back, having taken notice how <hi>apt</hi> your <hi>are</hi> to <hi>forget your ſelves:</hi> Look you now! whoſe was this <hi>Bracelet?</hi> Was this the Armies <hi>Declaration,</hi> or no? ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that and this now to be examined, never came from the <hi>ſame men;</hi> or <hi>thoſe men,</hi> are not <hi>the ſame</hi> they were—You begin with telling how unpleaſing it is to you to be <hi>neceſſitated</hi> to juſtifie <hi>your ſelves</hi> or your <hi>Actings</hi> to theſe <hi>Nations;</hi>—we never yet found you <hi>backward</hi> to <hi>ſay</hi> all that could be ſayd for your-ſelves: but I think it will be a hard mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to juſtifie your ſelves, or your Actings ſince 1652. and that may make it a little diſpleaſing, if you, or any body for you can do that, we will all go to <hi>School</hi> again; when you can <hi>juſtifie your ſelves,</hi> and <hi>actings:</hi> In firſt turning out this <hi>Parliament,</hi> then opening the <hi>Door</hi> for them <hi>again,</hi> as you ſay, <hi>you were bound in duty;</hi> and now <hi>ſhutting them out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain,</hi> and ſetting up <hi>Three and twenty Perſons,</hi> unto whom you have <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legated ſuch Power,</hi> as moſt <hi>honeſt men</hi> ſay, <hi>is not yours to give.</hi> I ſay, <hi>when you can juſtifie your ſelves herein,</hi> you ſhall be forgiven your <hi>former Treſpaſſes,</hi> and have as full <hi>Indempnity</hi> as your <hi>hearts can wiſh;</hi>—You go on—<hi>to do our ſelves Right,</hi> we muſt neceſſarily inſiſt upon the <hi>Miſcarriages</hi> of <hi>Others;</hi> of which we hold our ſelves <hi>obliged</hi> to give the <hi>People an Acount,</hi> and of our <hi>Proceedings</hi>—verily the <hi>People</hi> are much <hi>beholding</hi> to you: I doubt you would make a <hi>bad reckoning</hi> o'nt, if the <hi>People</hi> were enabled to <hi>call you to account:</hi> We ſee the <hi>ARMY</hi> to juſtifie <hi>themſelves;</hi> reſolve (as they are <hi>obliged by neceſſity</hi>) to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt upon the <hi>Failings</hi> of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and let them not <hi>ſpare:</hi> they have done their <hi>worſt;</hi> let every <hi>ſober minded</hi> man be aſſured; that the <hi>Parliament</hi> are <hi>free</hi> from any <hi>Imputations</hi> that <hi>malicious Tongues</hi> and <hi>Pens</hi> have <hi>uttered</hi> againſt them, which are not found in this <hi>black Bill:</hi> who are ſo ſure to ſay all that could be ſayd <hi>againſt them</hi> (and all <hi>little e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough</hi> to <hi>juſtifie themſelves</hi>) that they <hi>ſtrain hard</hi> to <hi>charge</hi> them with <hi>ſome things,</hi> that though they were <hi>true,</hi> yet are of little <hi>conſequence</hi> to <hi>juſtifie</hi> ſuch a <hi>proceeding</hi> in the <hi>Army;</hi> they turn every <hi>Stone</hi> to make <hi>Matter</hi> againſt <hi>them:</hi> But I muſt not <hi>anticipate</hi> thy <hi>Judgment;</hi> you ſhall ſee by and by, what the <hi>Mountain brings forth,</hi> and as you go along pray <hi>note</hi> how much they <hi>inſiſt</hi> upon their own <hi>Miſcarringes</hi> and <hi>Failings.</hi> Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thus Prefaced, you declare in theſe <hi>Words</hi>—<hi>Before the recal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the [late PARLIAMENT]</hi> Obſerve, it was the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> the Fifth of <hi>October</hi> laſt, as they <hi>ſtyle</hi> them in their <hi>Petition,</hi> and <hi>Repreſentation:</hi> But now the <hi>late Parliament!</hi> ſurely they are as much a <hi>Parliament</hi> now, as then; and if <hi>Six years force</hi> could not <hi>hinder them</hi> of being a <hi>Parliament,</hi> much leſs can <hi>Three weeks force:</hi> but the <hi>Jeſt</hi> is, they are the <hi>ſupreme Authority of the Nation,</hi> when the <hi>ARMY</hi> pleaſe to <hi>Chriſten them ſo:</hi> if the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> have any hopes they will <hi>ſerve their turn,</hi> then they are the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119208:4"/> of the Common-wealth of</hi> England: If they keep <hi>cloſe</hi> to the <hi>good</hi> of the <hi>Nation,</hi> then they are the (<hi>late Parliament</hi>—) We had divers <hi>Conſultations</hi> and <hi>Thoughts of heart,</hi> in what <hi>way</hi> and <hi>manner</hi> we might provide for the <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>good Government</hi> of this <hi>Common-wealth,</hi>—truth is, you have been very <hi>buſie</hi> all along; you <hi>break</hi> our <hi>Heads,</hi> and then think of <hi>Plaiſters for us:</hi> you <hi>broke</hi> this <hi>Parliament</hi> formerly, and after <hi>ſix years,</hi> when you found your <hi>own dirty Intereſts</hi> going <hi>down,</hi> then you had many <hi>Conſultations,</hi> how to <hi>keep them up:</hi> and when you could not go on your <hi>own way,</hi> the <hi>way</hi> you are now <hi>agoing,</hi> for the <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours</hi> of the <hi>People,</hi> and the <hi>interpoſing</hi> of your <hi>own inferiour Officers,</hi> you had ſome <hi>Conferences</hi> with ſome of the <hi>late Parliament,</hi> as you call them, from <hi>whom,</hi> it ſeems, receiving ſome <hi>good hopes</hi> of doing your <hi>Journey-work,</hi> you reſolve to put it to the <hi>Tryall,</hi> Whether they will be <hi>your Slaves,</hi> or the <hi>faithfull Servants</hi> of the <hi>People?</hi> Who having failed your <hi>Expectation,</hi> can be a <hi>Parliament no lo longer:</hi>—at length, calling to mind (no ſure, it was put in your <hi>Heads</hi> much againſt your <hi>Mindes</hi>) thoſe many great <hi>Things</hi> that had been <hi>effected</hi> for the <hi>good</hi> of theſe <hi>Nations,</hi> during the ſitting of <hi>the ſayd Parliament:</hi> Look back upon the <hi>Declaration</hi> of <hi>May</hi> 6. and ſee how it is there <hi>expreſſed,</hi>—Calling to minde, <hi>That the long Parliament conſiſting of the Members which continued there ſitting untill the Twentieth of</hi> April, 1653. <hi>were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent Aſſertors of the GOOD OLD CAUSE, and had a ſpeciall preſence of God with them, and were ſignally bleſſed in that Work.</hi> Read the very <hi>Words</hi> and obſerve a <hi>Juggle: That may be done during their ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that is not done by them.</hi> Make your own Obſervations,—and being likewiſe fully perſwaded, that the <hi>Government</hi> of theſe <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> might be moſt <hi>happily placed</hi> upon the <hi>Foundations</hi> of a <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth</hi> [and that upon <hi>ſuch Principles</hi> as was then agreed upon by us]—this is the <hi>Plague</hi> o'nt, they that for the moſt part of them, (<hi>Viz.</hi> The General Councel of <hi>Officers</hi>) muſt make a <hi>Mark</hi> for their <hi>Names;</hi> think themſelves ſo wiſe as to agree <hi>Principles</hi> among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, which are beſt for the Government of this <hi>Common-wealth:</hi> and what are theſe <hi>Principles?</hi> You ſhall find them in their <hi>Petition</hi> and <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs, May</hi> 12. 1659. the chief <hi>Corner Stones</hi> whereof are theſe;</p>
            <p>Article 12. <hi>We do unanimouſly acknowledge and own the Lord</hi> Charles Fleetwood <hi>to be Commander in chief of the Land Forces of this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Article 13. <hi>That there be a ſelect Senate Co-ordinate in Power with the Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Article 15. <hi>That all Debts contracted by his late Highneſs, or his Father, ſince the Fifteenth of</hi> December, 1653. <hi>may be ſatisfied, and that an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Revenue of Ten thouſand pounds</hi> per annum, <hi>with a convenient Houſe, may be ſetled upon him and his Heirs for ever, and Ten thouſand pounds more</hi> per annum, <hi>during his life, and upon his honourable Mother,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119208:4"/> Eight thouſand pound</hi> per annum, <hi>during her life: To the end, that a mark of the high eſteem this Nation hath of the good ſeruice done by his Father, our ever renowned Generall, may remain to Poſterity.</hi>—It concludes thus:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe having been the thoughts and deſires of our hearts, unanimouſly agreed upon, before your returning to ſit,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>You may judge whether theſe are not rare Principles to brag of <hi>A Senate to controul the Parliament:</hi> And <hi>Ten thouſand pound</hi> per annum, <hi>and a convenient Houſe for ever: Ten thouſand pound</hi> per annum <hi>for life for the Protector;</hi> and <hi>Eight thouſand pounds</hi> per annum <hi>for the old Dowager.</hi>—Upon my word, I do not know who contrived this ſo rarely; but 'tis a good Reward for making bold to rule us by his Will and pleaſure, to pay his Son and his Wife ſo well for it; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides what Rewards he took out of the <hi>Earle of Worceſters</hi> Eſtate, and what beſides he converted to his own Coffers. If I were Lord <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> I ſhould venture hard to make my ſelf <hi>ſome-body,</hi> if when the worſt came, my Heirs and Wife ſhould be ſo well rewarded: If when I could keep my Kingdome no longer, I ſhould be ſo well cared for, that my Son ſhould <hi>live like a Prince.</hi> Theſe are brave Principles for a Common-wealth, that the <hi>Council of Officers</hi> ſhould boaſt of:—You proceed,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And hoping through their experience of Affairs of Government, we might moſt ſafely deliver the Power, and Truſt of theſe Nations into their hands,</hi> (pardon me, you have done all you can to keep both in your own hands) <hi>and having thoſe further encouragements, that they having lyen under that rebuke for ſome years, which God hath given them for their former miſcarriages:</hi> That is, the Rebuke you had given them, when you turned out of the way; and turned them out of the Houſe, who you ſay your ſelves, <hi>Decl. May</hi> 6. <hi>were ſuch eminent Aſſertors of the GOOD OLD CAUSE, and had ſuch a ſpeciall preſence of God with them, that you judged it your Duty, to invite them again to diſcharge their Truſt;</hi> and really, 'tis their eminent aſſerting the <hi>GOOD OLD CAUSE,</hi> (and nothing elſe) that are the miſcarriages for which you ſo rudely rebuke them:—<hi>And alſo from ſome previous meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings with ſome worthy and leading Members of that Houſe,</hi> (theſe were I hope, none of thoſe the Army is now ſo angry at) <hi>who upon debate with us, approved of the Principles aforeſaid, and communicated them to ſome of their Fellow-Members.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mark here their debate, and the agreement of ſome Members with them in their Principles, of their Addreſſe, is a grand argument to perſwade them to readmit the Parliament. You finde no ſuch matter in <hi>Decl. May</hi> 6. But there it ſeems to be only <hi>conſcience of their ſin in diſturbing the Parliament, and wandring from equall and righteous paths; together with a ſenſe of their duty as bound to call them again, being ſuch
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119208:5"/> eminent Aſſertors of the</hi> GOOD CAUSE. This is ſtrange pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varication: It ſeems too, they were not ſo unſeigned in <hi>the ſhame they took to themſelves,</hi> for all the disfiguring of their faces, that they durſt truſt. God having done their duty; but muſt feel the <hi>Pulſe</hi> of ſome Members firſt, and give them their Leſſons, or the <hi>Principles</hi> they meant to inſiſt upon: So that they can <hi>take ſhame to themſelves,</hi> and yet drive on their Deſign; they are <hi>Maſters of Art</hi> in <hi>Diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,</hi> and can make Religion a <hi>Noſe of Waxe</hi> to ſerve their Intereſt: We were like to have our buſineſſe well managed by this <hi>praevious Meeting,</hi> if the Parliament had had ſo little <hi>honeſty,</hi> as the other <hi>wit.</hi>—</p>
            <p>That not only old diſpleaſures would have been forgotten (ſo they were) but that the ſingle, and ſetled Government of this Common-wealth would have been only aimed at.—So moſt men believe it was, having underſtood nothing to the contrary, but obſerved the Parliament very earneſt in contending for it; and had made a large progreſſe in it, even to admiration; though they had met with many Diſturbances, and not a few from your ſelves; but the miſchief is, <hi>that all this was not done in two moneths, that they might have died in Mount</hi> Nebo <hi>before now:</hi> But to ſhew what they might have done, and that two moneths was long enough in conſcience; their new 23 muſt ſettle a Government in ſix Weeks, <hi>and then I trow they may go to Mount</hi> Nebo <hi>and die too:</hi>—And although we were not ignorant, that by their former interruption, it was the opinion of many able, and learned perſons, that the late Parliament was wholly diſſolved—<hi>Speak out Gentle-folks, Mr.</hi> Pryn <hi>told you ſo; and what did he tell you beſides? Tell the whole truth.</hi> Doth not he tell you, <hi>You are Rebels, perjured perſons, Papiſts, Jeſuites, Sectaries:</hi> And is not this laſt as true as the firſt? If you knew them really diſſolved, <hi>why did you conjure them up again? Why would you put ſuch an abuſe upon the Nation? Why did you reſiſt Sir</hi> George Boothe <hi>to bloud, for denying them to be a Parliament?</hi> Surely, if this be true, <hi>you laid a Stumbling-block in your Brothers way,</hi> whoſe Bloud and Eſtate you yet ſeem vigorouſly to purſue: Certainly upon your heads muſt fall all the bloud that hath been ſpilt in this Quarrell: it is your ſin to ſet up an <hi>unjuſt power,</hi> not Sir <hi>George Booths</hi> to reſiſt ſuch a <hi>power.</hi> But why if this be true, do you ſo often ſtyle them <hi>The Supreme Authority?</hi> why doe you ſay, <hi>'tis your duty to call them again to their truſt: that it becomes you to yield them your utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt aſſiſtance to ſit in ſafety.</hi> Doth it become you do you think, to juggle thus <hi>before God and men; eſpecially ſince you were ſo well inſtructed of their being wholly diſſolved?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Good Lord, <hi>to what impudence ſhall we arrive ere long? and what may not prophane Wretches doe, if men that pretend ſo highly to</hi> Saintſhip <hi>dare deal thus? Lord, what wilt thou doe for thy Great Name?</hi> What a Reproach lies upon the <hi>Proteſtant Religion? Lord, roul away this
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119208:5"/> Reproach from us.</hi> And to this wretched ſhift is the Army driven, leſt they ſhould own them to be a <hi>Parliament:</hi> For if they were a Parliament, then they have no way of eſcape, but are <hi>Traytors with a witneſſe;</hi>—Yet being deſirous, like Drowning men (who are ready to catch hold of every twig) to lay hold on any thing that had the leaſt appearance of <hi>Civil Authority</hi>—This is pretty, ſo it ſeems, you now lay hold of another twig, I mean your 23. but that they want the leaſt appearance of <hi>Civil Authority</hi>—But do you think this is Chriſtian-like, <hi>to do evill that good may come of it?</hi> is this to <hi>abſtain from all appearance of evill?</hi> I cannot tell but this Twig may in time make you ſmart for your folly and wickedneſſe,—Thereby hoping to ſee the Nation eſtabliſhed upon the Baſis afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned. Mark that, <hi>They laid hold on this Parliament, hoping they would ſettle the Nation as the Army had contrived it in their Petition, and Addreſſe</hi> before mentioned: This is rare good ſport, is it not? <hi>Therefore—we did think fit in our Declaration of the</hi> 6 <hi>of</hi> May, (nay, you ſay there, <hi>You judged it your duty,</hi> it is one thing <hi>to think fit,</hi> another thing <hi>to think it your duty</hi>) <hi>to invite the Members of that Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> &amp;c. Look back a little, and obſerve, whether the reaſons they alleadge there, that perſwade them <hi>of their duty to call the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> and the conceits they mention here, which made them <hi>think fit to invite them,</hi> doe well agree: I think you finde few of the former reaſons in this Declaration, and as few of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe Conceits in the former Declaration. Pray ſtay here a little, and meditate, it will be worth your while: There you may obſerve, they confeſſe, <hi>they had wandred divers wayes from equall, and righteous paths; and that God diſappointed all Eſſayes for ſettlement;</hi> that <hi>the GOOD OLD CAUSE became a Reproach, and the good Spirit that formerly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared among us began to decline, and did daily decline; and being led to look back and examine the cauſe of Gods departing from them, and where they turned out of the way, that they might return, and give him glory. And calling to minde, that this Parliament were eminent Aſſertors of the</hi> GOOD OLD CAUSE, <hi>and had a ſpeciall preſence of God with them, and were ſignally bleſſed in that work; therefore they judged it their duty to invite, and did moſt earneſtly deſire them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the exerciſe of their Truſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is all that? is it no more then this, <hi>calling to minde what great things were effected during their ſitting?</hi> or is there ever a word of your own thoughts of he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rt; that they were the beſt Principles and fitteſt to bottome the Common-wealth upon, that you agreed among your ſelves. No, we immediately ſaw it was but a faigned Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and a partiall ſhame, when we read your <hi>Addreſſe</hi> of the 12. <hi>May,</hi> of which I gave you notice in Print: Have you any ſuch mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive there, as the experience of this Parliament in affairs of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119208:6"/> that you mention in that Declaration, <hi>May</hi> 6. to induce you to deliver the power and truſt of the Nation into their hands; not a word I warrant you to this purpoſe, nor yet of ſuch an encouragement us this, <hi>that the Parliament having lyen under the rebuke of God, for their former miſcarriages, would be like to follow him more cloſe now in the wayes leading to peace and righteouſneſſe;</hi> nor a word of any <hi>previous meetings with any Leading Members of the Houſe,</hi> and their approving of the Armies <hi>thoughts of heart;</hi> nor yet of laying hold upon them only as that which had only an appearance of <hi>Authority.</hi> I am ſorry to have occaſion for ſuch work as this—Minde your <hi>Preface</hi> in your Addreſſe, <hi>May</hi> 12.—<hi>Calling to mind the former Declarations of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and the grounds therein inviting us to take up Arms; and thoſe many ſignall providences wherein the Lord hath owned you, and your Forces by Sea and Land, in aſſerting that Righteous Cauſe; wherein the Civil and Religious Liberties of the People are involved, ſo as all open oppoſition was beaten down before you; and likewiſe weighing with our ſelves, how in theſe ſeverall Changes of Government, that publick Spirit that appeared in that work, hath ſince that time been diſcouraged,</hi> (that is, ſince the Parliament was firſt diſturbed by <hi>Cromwell</hi>) <hi>and another raiſed up, drawing back to the things you had contended againſt, even to the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarding the Eſſentials of that Cauſe: We did upon ſerious thoughts of heart think it our Duty to appear againſt thoſe back ſliding wayes once more; And the good Providence of God holding forth an opportunity to us to open unto you a way for the further diſcharge of your remaining Truſt, in Parliament; we did by our Declaration</hi> May 6. <hi>humbly deſire you would be pleaſed to return to the exerciſe &amp; diſcharge thereof.</hi> I only lay theſe things before thee: Judge righteous judgement.—<hi>Soon after their ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, We preſented our Addreſſe, to which we had to our great content, ample aſſurance of their good acceptance, expreſt not only by their hearty thanks, but by approving many things therein contained, and referring the reſt to Committees of their Members.</hi>—Mark—'Tis moſt certain the Parliament did all man could doe, to keep fair with them, and did grant any thing they deſired, ſo farre as they might not enſlave the people, by a <hi>Senate;</hi> or give away their Money againſt all reaſon; to maintain them in Pomp, who roſe to ſuch a height by the ruine of the Nation.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, they petitioned that a godly, faithfull and painfull <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery</hi> be every where encouraged, countenanced and maintained; but the Parliament could not preſently finde a better maintenance then <hi>Tythes</hi> for that purpoſe; neither did the Army petition to have Tythes taken away, though now it ſeems they are reſolved upon; though I doubt, they do not yet know, which way to provide ſo well for them: nor could the Parliament think taking away Tythes could be a likely means that every where ſuch a Miniſtry be encouraged, countenanced, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> maintained.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:119208:6"/>
            <p>—But now comes on the <hi>Charge,</hi> now it is that they <hi>juſtifie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> by inſiſting upon the <hi>Miſcarriages</hi> of the <hi>Parliament,</hi>—Firſt and foremoſt the <hi>Act of Oblivion</hi> was long before it was paſſed, and then moſt <hi>imperfect</hi> and <hi>ineffectuall</hi> for the <hi>Ends</hi> expected,—that it <hi>ſtuck</hi> long in hand is no <hi>great wonder,</hi> for if it had eaſily paſſed, it might have given too much <hi>encouragement</hi> for <hi>new Deſigns</hi> upon the <hi>Government;</hi> but it came out at laſt, that is ſure enough, but now 'tis miſerably <hi>imperfect,</hi> and <hi>ineffectuall</hi> to the <hi>Ends</hi> expected: though this were true, yet 'tis <hi>ſcurvy dealing</hi> on your ſide; why did you not put the <hi>Parliament</hi> in mind of it in your <hi>Petition,</hi> and <hi>Repreſentation,</hi> and deſire its <hi>amendment?</hi> you have had time enough to do it, as doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs you would have done, if that <hi>Act</hi> had not done its <hi>buſineſs</hi> pretty well: but we do not know what you mean by the <hi>Ends</hi> expected, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs you would have had full <hi>Indempnity</hi> for what ever you have done, or ſhall do amiſs to your lives end: <hi>Indempnity</hi> for keeping out the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> formerly, and <hi>Indempnity</hi> for ſhutting them out now, and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempnity</hi> for turning out every <hi>Authority</hi> that ſhall not pleaſe you: this would do wondrous well indeed to the <hi>Ends expected;</hi> but I hope this <hi>Imperfection</hi> is only the opinion of thoſe Learned and able men that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded you the <hi>Parliament</hi> was wholly <hi>diſſolved:</hi> notwithſtanding which you made every body to <hi>own them</hi> for the <hi>ſupreme Authority,</hi> and took the Money they levied for you, as if they had been a <hi>Parliament;</hi> and no queſtion their <hi>Act of Indempnity</hi> will ſerve your turn one time or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, one way or another,—and for what concerned our twelve <hi>Propoſalls,</hi> wherein we owned the Lord <hi>Fleetwood</hi> to be <hi>Commander i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> chief</hi> of the Land Forces of this <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> and concerning which we had aſſurance given, that the ſame ſhould be <hi>granted in Parliament;</hi>—verily this is <hi>excellent,</hi> who could give you <hi>aſſurance?</hi> theſe <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralls</hi> ſignifie nothing: was it Sir <hi>Henry Vaune,</hi> who promiſed and vowed this thing in their <hi>Name?</hi> you are hard put to it I perceive,—we were not leſs deceived in our <hi>Expectation</hi> (very ſtrange the <hi>Parliament</hi> durſt do any otherwiſe then as you ſhould direct them: to what a <hi>pitch</hi> of <hi>Pride</hi> are <hi>theſe Men grown!</hi> who but a while ſince a great many of them I ſhould hardly have <hi>numbred with the Dogs of my Flock</hi>) his <hi>Commiſſion</hi> being reſtrained to <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> (verily this is a <hi>criticall piece,</hi> we would have him Commander <hi>in chief</hi> of the Land Forces of the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> and his <hi>Commiſſion</hi> is reſtrained to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Scotland:</hi> he ſhould have been <hi>Commander in chief</hi> of <hi>Jamaica</hi> too one would think by the ſtory—upon my word you make <hi>hard ſhift</hi> to <hi>pick Quarrells:</hi> Doth any body think if the <hi>Parliament</hi> had gone about to <hi>oppreſs the Nation</hi> in the leaſt, that they would have <hi>routed</hi> in ſuch <hi>Holes as theſe</hi> to have found out the <hi>Sluts corner?</hi> Verily I am much pleaſed to ſee them in theſe <hi>Straights</hi>—his <hi>Commiſſion</hi> was limited to the ſixth day of <hi>May,</hi> or to be revoked <hi>at pleaſure</hi>—
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119208:7"/> was this ever til now thought to be ſuch an <hi>hainous Crim?</hi> what ſhould tho <hi>Parliament</hi> give <hi>ſuch a Power</hi> that they could not <hi>recall?</hi> this would make the <hi>Commander in chief</hi> Coſm German to a <hi>ſingle PROTECTOR:</hi> What give a <hi>Sword</hi> into <hi>mad mens</hi> hands! You have uſed the <hi>Sword</hi> ſo well formerly, that 'tis not good <hi>truſting you further then we can ſee you;</hi> ſtill 'tis better and better: you ſee the <hi>Miſcarciages</hi> the <hi>Parliament</hi> were <hi>guilty of</hi>—and the further to abridge him of his <hi>Authority,</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily belonging to him, to keep the <hi>Army in good order</hi> (that is, to make them for his own intereſt—) and to make the <hi>Army</hi> wholly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervient to their <hi>Will;</hi> I pray to whoſe <hi>Will</hi> ſhould they be <hi>ſubſervient?</hi> to the <hi>Parliaments,</hi> or my <hi>Lord Fleetwoods:</hi> (O groſs <hi>Miſcarriages</hi> of the <hi>Parliament</hi>) they reſolved that all <hi>Commiſſions</hi> ſhould be given by Mr. <hi>Speaker,</hi> this indeed is a <hi>grievous one,</hi> but I think pretty well agreeing with the <hi>Principles</hi> of a <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> which nevertheleſs was ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto by the <hi>Army</hi> for Peace ſake, not for <hi>Conſcience ſake</hi> it ſeems; that is to ſay, <hi>rather then loſe their ſweet Offices and Commands,</hi> they ſubmitted for <hi>Peace ſake,</hi> as no queſtion they would to the <hi>Turk</hi> rather then fail; though not a few of theſe <hi>Sparks</hi> made very <hi>learned Speeches,</hi> and <hi>fair Promiſes</hi> of their <hi>faithfulneſs</hi> to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and ſeemed high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to reſent the <hi>Parliaments Favour</hi> in thinking them worthy of ſuch <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments;</hi> and yet after all this you ſee what 'tis come to, and a rare <hi>Principle</hi> you have introduced to be a <hi>Foundation</hi> for your <hi>Free State,</hi> that I may take a <hi>Commiſſion</hi> from you, and <hi>receive your Pay,</hi> and yet when I ſee my time, <hi>turn your own Swords upon you:</hi> If ſome men ſhould deal thus with you, they <hi>payd you in your own Coyn:</hi> and you could not refuſe to take it in <hi>currant payment</hi>—What Factions hereupon grew up in the <hi>Army?</hi> what new <hi>moulding, changing,</hi> and <hi>transforming</hi> thereof, to the diſcompoſure of the whole? how <hi>Parties</hi> were <hi>made</hi> and <hi>headed,</hi> and <hi>encouraged</hi> by divers <hi>Members</hi> ſitting in <hi>Parliament</hi>—This is <hi>excellent;</hi> was that ever counted <hi>Faction</hi> before, which is only <hi>Conſcience of duty</hi> and <hi>honeſty:</hi> ſome of the <hi>Commanders</hi> of the <hi>Army</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>bewailed</hi> their <hi>Apoſtaſy</hi> among the reſt, thought it too much <hi>ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of hypocriſie</hi> to go over their <hi>old Leſſon</hi> again, and <hi>dictate a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> having been ſenſible of their little <hi>good ſpeed</hi> before, yea, and bewailed it too in theſe very words, <hi>Declar, May</hi> 6. although there have been many Eſſayes, (that is, they had made many Eſſayes ſince the <hi>diſturbing of the Parliament,</hi> as by the ſenſe of that <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration</hi> you muſt needs underſtand it) to <hi>obviate dangers,</hi> and ſettle theſe <hi>Nations in Peace</hi> and <hi>Proſperity;</hi> yet all have proved <hi>ineffectuall,</hi> the only wiſe GOD in the courſe of his Providence diſappointing all <hi>Endeavours</hi> therein: I ſay, theſe men obſerving upon what <hi>Rocks</hi> you had run by your own confeſſion, thought it good <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> to <hi>acquieſſe</hi> in the wiſdome of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> whom you had ſo earneſtly deſired to return to their <hi>Truſt;</hi> your ſelves hoping that through their <hi>Experience</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:119208:7"/> in Affairs of <hi>Government,</hi> as you ſtill ſay, you might ſafely deliver the <hi>Truſt</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> of the <hi>Nation</hi> into their hands: Theſe are the very words of your new <hi>Declaration:</hi> is this <hi>Faction</hi> to be ſatisfied in their <hi>Reſolutions</hi> to whom you had committed the <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Truſt?</hi> yes verily that is <hi>Faction,</hi> that will not <hi>turn with every wind</hi> and <hi>breath</hi> of your <hi>changling Councel of Officers:</hi> they had taken their <hi>Commiſſions</hi> from the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and were not well convinced of the neceſſity that lay upon them to be <hi>perfidious,</hi> but thought fit to be <hi>conſtant</hi> to their <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Truſt,</hi> and this is <hi>Faction;</hi> upon my word 'tis well <hi>defined:</hi> I did not ſo throughly underſtand <hi>Faction</hi> before; the <hi>new moulding, changing,</hi> and <hi>transforming,</hi> you make ſuch ado about, is no more but this, <hi>you put out ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſingle perſon men out of your Army,</hi> as <hi>Gough, Ingoldsby, Whaly, Mills, Falconbridge, Howard,</hi> and in their places the <hi>Parliament</hi> put in ſuch as had been <hi>right for a Common-wealth</hi> (except <hi>Lambert</hi> and <hi>Packer,</hi> two of your <hi>own Creatures</hi>) as <hi>Okey, Rich, Overton, Alured Saunders;</hi> none were put out but <hi>Protectorians,</hi> ſuch as you had <hi>pointed at,</hi> or <hi>put out before;</hi> and none <hi>brought in,</hi> ſaving <hi>only thoſe</hi> you <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> them in, but <hi>ſuch</hi> as had <hi>declared themſelves</hi> ſufficiently for a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth:</hi> moſt of whom you approved, unleſs <hi>Rich</hi> and <hi>Overton,</hi> and one or two more, whom you thought would <hi>not comply enough,</hi> but were <hi>too honeſt</hi> for ſuch <hi>Company—Parties</hi> were <hi>made, headed,</hi> and <hi>encouraged,</hi> by <hi>Members of Parliament; Made, Headed, and encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged!</hi> here are a great many words together to make up this <hi>Crime;</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>Colonell Morley,</hi> and Sir <hi>Arthur Haſterigge,</hi> the latter of whom was laid by <hi>formerly</hi> by the <hi>Protector,</hi> for being a <hi>true Friend</hi> to the <hi>Liberties of this Nation,</hi> and an <hi>Eminent Aſſertor</hi> of the <hi>Principles</hi> of a <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> who expoſed himſelf to the fury of <hi>the Court,</hi> by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending for <hi>Englands Birth-right,</hi> when the beſt <hi>H E</hi> in the <hi>Army</hi> durſt not <hi>ſpeak a word for it,</hi> and hath ten thouſand times more <hi>Honeſty</hi> then <hi>all theſe Officers together,</hi> who never yet had occaſion to bewail his <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſie,</hi> ſince 1653. for <hi>complying</hi> and <hi>acting</hi> under every <hi>Government:</hi> and <hi>Morly</hi> I think is one of thoſe <hi>Eminent Aſſertors</hi> of the <hi>Good Cauſe</hi> your <hi>Declaration, May</hi> 6. ſpeaks of, and <hi>one of thoſe</hi> whoſe <hi>Experience</hi> in the <hi>Affairs of Government,</hi> gave you hopes you might give the <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Truſt</hi> of the <hi>Nation</hi> into <hi>their hands:</hi> Me thinks then he might be truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Command a Regiment;</hi> and this is the <hi>ſad ſtory</hi> they tell, of <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king</hi> and <hi>heading Parties,</hi> unleſs Lieutenant General <hi>Ludlow</hi>'s <hi>Command</hi> in <hi>Ireland ſtick in their ſtomachs,</hi> who is as <hi>honeſt</hi> as the <hi>beſt Commander</hi> of your <hi>now Councell:</hi> a <hi>ſad Crime indeed,</hi> that two or three <hi>Parliament Men</hi> ſhould have <hi>Commandes</hi> in the <hi>Army,</hi> when we remember how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rny <hi>Commanders</hi> of the <hi>Army</hi> got in the <hi>late Protect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rrs Parliament:</hi> and what ſin is <hi>the one,</hi> more then <hi>the other?</hi> but all the <hi>Miſchief</hi> is, that Word <hi>(Encouraged)</hi> the <hi>Parliament</hi> did all that could be done to <hi>pay the Army,</hi> and therein gave them <hi>great Encouragement,</hi> that they
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119208:8"/> ſhould not be ſo <hi>in Arrear,</hi> as they had been uſed to be: and this was the <hi>Crime,</hi> ſo that the Army began to ſee they had <hi>mended their Maſters,</hi> and generally were much ſatisfied with the <hi>Parliaments Proceedings,</hi> which it ſeems began to <hi>ſteal away their hearts</hi> from the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of the <hi>Great Officers,</hi> which in time might have made them too well to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand <hi>themſelves,</hi> to turn with every pretenſe of the <hi>Great Officers,</hi> and believe me 'twas time to look to this; 'tis not fit any body ſhould <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the Army</hi> but <hi>themſelves: Lambert</hi> may give them a thouſand pounds at a time to <hi>Encourage</hi> his <hi>Officers</hi> to be his <hi>Janniſaries:</hi> but the <hi>poor Soldiers</hi> muſt not be <hi>Encouraged</hi> by the <hi>Parliament.</hi> What a <hi>ſad Predicament</hi> are our <hi>Parliaments</hi> brought into; if they had not <hi>Encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged</hi> the Soldiers, then that had been a <hi>Crime with a witneſs:</hi> What take no <hi>Care of them</hi> that venture <hi>their Lives for you?</hi> how often are the <hi>Parliament twitted</hi> in the <hi>Armies Repreſentation</hi> and <hi>Petition</hi> for their <hi>Rebukes</hi> upon the Proceedings of ſome of the <hi>Northern Brigade;</hi> what miſunderſtand their <hi>humble Servants</hi> that had ventured their <hi>Lives</hi> for them with ſo <hi>good Succeſs,</hi> and now 'tis their <hi>Crime</hi> that they <hi>Encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged</hi> the <hi>Soldery:</hi> Good Lord! what is not a <hi>Crime,</hi> if the <hi>Army</hi> pleaſe <hi>to call it ſo?</hi> We have brought our <hi>Hoggs</hi> to a <hi>fair Market</hi>—and ſtrengthned, not only by bringing divers perſons into <hi>Commands</hi> of prejudiced minds; you would do well to inſtance in any one man brought in of a prejudiced mind to a <hi>Common-wealth Government,</hi> but a few of your own <hi>Creatures;</hi> As the <hi>Inſtrument Maker,</hi> and that Valiant <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimator,</hi> Colonel <hi>Packer:</hi> unleſs you mean men of prejudiced <hi>Mindes</hi> to your former <hi>Wayes,</hi> who were turned out becauſe they would not <hi>bow their Knees to Baal:</hi> As <hi>Okey, Rich, Overton, Alured, Saunders,</hi> and ſome others: theſe did ſtrengthen the <hi>Common wealths Principles,</hi> though very like they might believe the <hi>Parliament</hi> would provide better for the Nation, <hi>then your thoughts of heart and Conſultations</hi> had agreed among your ſelves: theſe ſtrengthen <hi>Faction,</hi> becauſe they would not ſtrengthen your <hi>Hands</hi> to ſet up the <hi>Brat</hi> of your <hi>own Brains,</hi> but thought it better wiſdome to expect ſettlement from the <hi>Parliament,</hi> who, as you ſay your ſelves, <hi>were ſignally bleſſed of God, when your ſelves never thrived in any Deſign, but in unſetling and ruining us</hi>—And by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving faithful Officers into remote parts of this Common wealth, without any cauſe ſhewn, or Conſultations had with the <hi>Commander in chief</hi> thereupon, which is not only notoriouſly known unto all that are concerned in <hi>Military Affairs, but obvious to common Obſervation</hi>—O brave, <hi>Here is a Charge with a witneſs;</hi> What is the myſtery of this Buſineſs? <hi>I think few are acquainted with the Hiſtory of it.</hi> the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may not order the Forces they <hi>Pay,</hi> where they think moſt fit to diſpoſe of them, <hi>for the ſecurity of the Nation;</hi> but muſt ask their Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant General leave firſt: ſurely if this had been a matter of any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, their <hi>Petition and Repreſentation</hi> would have rung a Peal in the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119208:8"/> Parliaments eans about it; and they would have been more expreſs, and particular in the Charge; But 'tis an Old Cheat to put things into Generall terms, and to ſeem mighty conſident of what is ſaid; that by the former one might more hardly undeceive ones ſelf, by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of particulars; and by the latter might be more obliged to believe that which they lay down as a matter notoriouſly known, and ſo not worthy of particular inſtance: I profeſſe my own ignorance in the matter, ſo as it may make a Charge, and deſie you to inſtance in particulars; which till you have done, I tell you, <hi>You lie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—<hi>By which means the aforementioned deſign of a generall Inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection took further incouragement, ſpreeding it ſelf into every part of this Nation, and being now grown ripe (though by the wonderfull good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God prevented in other places) broke out in</hi> Cheſhiere—</p>
            <p>O malice, maliced you had beſt ſay, as ſome of your Sneaking Creatures have ſaid, <hi>That the Parliament had a hand in Sir</hi> George Booths <hi>Plot.</hi> It had been better for the ſecurity of the Nation, if more of thoſe ſeditious Officers, and their Forces, had been diſpoſed into every Quarter of <hi>England,</hi> and not kept loytering about <hi>London,</hi> to have awed the Parliament, and kept their Counſells to dictate to them. This was that gave ſo much encouragement to the Plot; the Officers of the Army lye plotting at <hi>London,</hi> and neglect their Charge, and in the mean time they took opportunity to plot in the <hi>Countrey:</hi> And this muſt be laid at the Parliaments dore. And whereas the Plot in moſt places was prevented, <hi>this,</hi> ſnith the Declaration, <hi>was by the wounderfull goodneſſe of God;</hi> but never a word of the <hi>Parliaments</hi> or <hi>Council of States</hi> wiſdome, in diſpoſing of our Forces ſo as thoy were almoſt every where in readineſſe to attend them: And if the Officers of the Army had been as they ſhould be, many of thoſe Forces that lay at <hi>London,</hi> might have been in <hi>Cheſh ere,</hi> and prevented that danger too.</p>
            <p>—<hi>For the ſuppreſſion of which, a convenient number of the Army were appointed to march under</hi> Lambert, (Who appointed them?) <hi>and through the Bleſſing of God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>were routed, and ſubdued.</hi> See, here is never a word of the <hi>Parliaments,</hi> or the <hi>Council of States</hi> quick and almoſt miraculous bringing over the Forces from <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kirk;</hi> no, their buſineſſe now, is not to commend the ſignall preſence of God with the <hi>Parliament:</hi> theſe are Brave Youths.</p>
            <p>—<hi>The ſull ſeace of which Mercy, put it into the hearts of ſome of the Officers of that part of the Army, to meet, and conſider how the ſame might be improved to the glory of God, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This makes my hair ſtare, that men dare ſpeak after this rate; but 'tis the Old Chear with which we have been too long bewitched; the Officers met, to conſider how they might improve their mercies to the glory of God; and they roated this Parliament; and did ſo again;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119208:9"/> and called the <hi>Mock-Parliament;</hi> and again too and routed them; once more, and made their Protector; yes, and they improved that to the glory of God too, and made him Protector for ever, thought fit for the glory of God, that he ſhould nominate his Succeſſor; yes, and for the glory of God too ſet up the <hi>Other Houſe,</hi> and many of them were Members thereof: Aie, and for the glory of God too pulled down the Protector, and both his one Houſe and his other Houſe; and then for the <hi>GOOD OLD CAUSE,</hi> and the glory of God, <hi>who,</hi> they ſay, <hi>had withdrawn his wonted preſence from them,</hi> invite this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſit again, becauſe when they were turned out before, the Army then thought, and ſay, <hi>they turned out of the way;</hi> and now, through <hi>mercy, they return to give him the glory:</hi> Very good, and now the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Brigade, for to improve the glory of God, muſt improve the glory of their Great Commander; muſt have a <hi>Generall,</hi> and <hi>Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Generall,</hi> and <hi>Major Generall,</hi> &amp;c. Yes too, and to improve the glory of God, they muſt turn out the Parliament again; vote all null and void that the Parliament did which diſpleaſed them; yes, and for the glory of God too, they muſt have the ſole power of placing and diſplacing their Officers; yes, and for the glory of God, they muſt act without Commiſſions, and againſt Commiſſions; take the whole care of the Nation into their own hands, make <hi>Flcetwood</hi> Commader in Chief, that is in Engliſh, <hi>Generall; Lambert</hi> the next man to him, and <hi>Deſborough</hi> next to him; yes, and for the glory of God too, it was ſet upon their Spirits, after ſeeking of God, to create a <hi>Council of State,</hi> or <hi>Committee of Safety,</hi> into whoſe hands they have <hi>given all power;</hi> that <hi>whoſoevers ſins they remit, ſhall be remitted;</hi> and <hi>whatever they binde on earth, ſhall be bound in heaven,</hi> or among the Saints at <hi>Wallingford-houſe, if they like it,</hi> that muſt be alwayes underſtood: And I dare lay odds, that ere long, for the glory of God, it will be put upon their hearts to lay them aſide too: 'tis for the glory of God too, no doubt, that it is now upon their ſpirits, to finde a <hi>Better main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance</hi> for the Miniſtry then <hi>Tythes;</hi> to reform the Law, or rather <hi>to be a Law to themſelves.</hi> But 'tis no wonder if they mend the Law, ſince the Articles of Warre, it ſeems, want ſome Reformation; yes, and 'tis for the glory of God too out of all queſtion, that to juſtifie themſelves, they muſt not only inſiſt upon the failings of others; but make the World believe ſtrange things, when they cannot ſay one word to the purpoſe to condemn the Parliament, or juſtifie themſelves, but in ſuch a way of juggling, diſſembling and double meaning, that no Chriſtian durſt declare at ſuch a rate. Theſe are ſo notoriouſly the Products of your Conſultations for the improvement of Gods glory, that not a Childe in the Streets almoſt but will ſay, <hi>Is the Army a faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? ſurely ſome miſchief is a working;</hi> and they have Propheſied for the moſt part. For Gods ſake either be more <hi>boneſt,</hi> or boaſt not ſo
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119208:9"/> much of your <hi>Religion;</hi> thoſe things that have been done by you, had been horrid Crimes in them that <hi>never heard or believed in a Jeſus.</hi> O this <hi>Religion,</hi> theſe pretenſes of yours, wherein you are wonderous dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous, hath done your work hitherto, and fooled many honeſt hearts to a compliance with you; <hi>For which perhaps the next Age may fame you, with, The moſt infamous Crew of</hi> Munſter.</p>
            <p>—Whereupon they reſolved upon a Paper, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that is the Paper wherein they deſire a Generall, and other generall Officers; <hi>This is for the glory of God:</hi> but it will never be better as long as thoſe buſie bodies take ſo much upon them; there is no doubt but as long as you eſſay to obviate dangers, and ſettle the Nation, by ſuch <hi>Principles</hi> as you agree among your ſelves, you will have ever now and then occaſion to look back where you <hi>turned out of the way;</hi> as long as you ſay to the <hi>Parliament—You take too much upon you, all the Congregation or Camp are holy,</hi> we ſhall never ſee a better World; 'tis your medling hath done all our <hi>Miſchief:</hi> This Paper, ſaith the <hi>Declaration, was ſent to</hi> Fleetwood, <hi>and his Excellency deſiring to put the ſame into ſuch a way, as might not ſavour of Offence to the Parliament,</hi> Conſulted with Sir <hi>Arthur Haſterigge</hi> thereupon, as alſo with <hi>Vaune,</hi> and <hi>Salway;</hi> all which were to conſult what was fit to be done: <hi>Marke how fain they would have drawn in honeſt Sir</hi> Arthur, <hi>who could never yet be drawn off from the Intereſt of his Country, and his faithfulneſs to them;</hi> and judge what courſe was like to be taken in it, by what courſe hath been taken ſince, notwithſtanding the diſlike the <hi>Parliament</hi> manifeſted againſt it, being alſo to be counſelled by <hi>Vane</hi> and <hi>Salway, two very precious Pieces</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—But the next day Sir <hi>Arthur</hi> informed the <hi>Houſe</hi> of the ſaid Paper; <hi>Yes, and I think he had been a Knave if he had not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—Whereupon the Houſe poſſeſt with prejudice upon this miſ-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation: <hi>Mark that here,</hi> and in ſome places afterwards they would needs perſwade us the <hi>Parliament are ſuch Fools, (as themſelves) to be led by the Noſes by two or three Grandees.</hi> 'Tis well we know them better: and the conſequence proves them to have been in no miſtake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this matter; <hi>None but ſuch Woodcocks would make themſelves ſo ridiculous as to go about to perſwade us that the Parliament did not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand themſelves as well as the Generall Councell—fell into high Debates, expreſſing great heat and anger againſt the Lord</hi> Lambert (I wonder how he came to be a Lord) <hi>and ſeverall, other faithfull Officers of the Brigade, from whence the Paper came.</hi> I wonder who told you this Newes, he was a worſhipfull Member that thus told Tales out of Shcool, and knows, or ſhould know what he deferves for his pains? 'tis fit this were a little redreſſed; but was it ever denied a Member to ſpeak his Mind in the Houſe, though it were againſt the King himſelf, or rather his Councel? I think the Houſe is free, ſome ſpake freely enough in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119208:10"/> the Houſe not long ſince againſt <hi>Protectorſhip,</hi> and again the other Houſe, &amp; yet I never heard <hi>that ſin layd to their charge:</hi> what is it an unpardona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſin to expreſs ſome anger againſt <hi>Lambert</hi> in <hi>Parliament?</hi> I think they were too tender of him; <hi>And if they could have done more, and ſayd leſs it had been better for the Nation</hi>—although they were truly informed by the Lord <hi>Fleetwood, That</hi> Lambert <hi>gave no conſent, nor had any hand in it.</hi> ('Tis true he went into <hi>Yorkſhire</hi> on purpoſe, as it is ſaid, that he might diſſemble it the better) but do you think any man in his right wits will believe it: no queſtion, he that made a former Inſtrument, plaid a little upon this too—But endeavoured the ſuppreſſion thereof, both before and after his coming to Town: Did you ever read the like <hi>Impudence?</hi> do you imagine he that could ſuppreſs the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> could not ſuppreſs a <hi>poor Paper; ſure you take us to be very blooks</hi>—ſo that now it was apparent that thoſe <hi>Factions</hi> already ſaid <hi>(Caſtles in the Aire)</hi> began to purſue what they had in proſpect, and deſign (what was that? <hi>why a free Common-wealth</hi>) more openly and vigorouſly then before: as how for example, <hi>Why by Voting that any other Generall Officers then what were already, were chargable, dangerous, and unneceſſary:</hi> for that was the deſign of the Paper to have a Generall and generall Officers; if that had not been the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, you would have heard of it in the <hi>Petition</hi> and <hi>repreſentation</hi> you may be ſure: nor do they deny it (but diſſemble it) here, and make you believe they will expoſe it to publick View; <hi>I believe ſo at latter Lammas,</hi> or <hi>when they have licked it into another ſhape:</hi> and yet theſe men are utterly againſt <hi>a ſingle Perſon,</hi> or <hi>Peers;</hi> mark the iſſue on't, if they be not ſtopt in their Career—</p>
            <p>Hereupon the Officers of the Army thought it their duty to repreſent to the <hi>Parliament</hi> (what your duty, when you knew that before they were wholly diſſolved) their <hi>Innocency;</hi> and to obviate the aforemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Deſigns <hi>(you have underſtood before what thoſe Deſigns were)</hi> to deſire <hi>(or rather to will and require)</hi> that the Army might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their Commiſſions, with the Advice of ſuch perſons, who by experience had the knowledge of their Abilities, and fitneſs for ſervice: See now how much concerned they are to <hi>ſhrink away the ſhoulder from the Parliament;</hi> O this taking Commiſſions from the <hi>Parliament</hi> went to their <hi>hearts,</hi> but yet 'tis no bar againſt turning them out: I wonder who were more fit to judge of the Ability of any perſons for Imployment then the <hi>Councell of State?</hi> why might they not ſerve turn for a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Nomination?</hi> and I think you can rarely name a man that had any <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> but who were firſt preſented either by the <hi>Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee of Nominations,</hi> or the <hi>Councell of State,</hi> unleſs ſome men that were too well known to be ſuſpected of unfitneſs for ſuch an <hi>Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>—And that they might not be turned out Arbitrarily (give an inſtance of one that was ſo turned out if you can) but by the uſuall
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119208:10"/> and known way of a Court Marſhall: was this ever an uſuall or known way, that the Court Marſhall ſhould be above the <hi>Parliament,</hi> if a <hi>Parliament</hi> think fit to put out a <hi>Commander,</hi> and the <hi>Court Martiall</hi> think it not fit, then that <hi>Commander</hi> ſhall keep his place in deſpight of the <hi>Parliament:</hi> and yet theſe be the men that intend not to ſet up a <hi>Military Power</hi> in this <hi>Nation:</hi> I wonder whether the <hi>Parliament</hi> asked the <hi>Court Martiall</hi> leave, when they at one clap Voted all the Membert of the <hi>Parliament</hi> too out of their <hi>Commands</hi> in the <hi>Army:</hi> when they took away <hi>Eſſex</hi> his <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> and all the <hi>Officers</hi> of his <hi>Army,</hi> and formed a <hi>new Army,</hi> diſplacing any <hi>Officer</hi> as they ſaw occaſion; and if this be denied the <hi>Parliament</hi> now, 'tis becauſe <hi>their Servants are their Maſters:</hi> for whoever hath this Power, if the <hi>Court Martiall</hi> muſt have it, Ile warrant them <hi>the Supreme Authority of the Nation</hi>—</p>
            <p>And laſtly, Aſſerting the <hi>Libertie</hi> and <hi>Rights</hi> belonging to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>&amp;c. Surreverence in your Teeth:</hi> you aſſert the <hi>Liberties of the People:</hi> that's a very good one; if we had no better Aſſertors of our <hi>Liberties</hi> then you, we might think ourſelves happy under <hi>WILL.</hi> the <hi>Conqueror,</hi> you aſſert our <hi>Liberties</hi> bravely by doing what you pleaſe, ſetting up what Power your ſelves pleaſe, and pulling down as often as they <hi>diſpleaſe</hi> you: you have beggered the <hi>Nation</hi> almoſt, and tell us ſtories of aſſerting our <hi>Liberties:</hi> but ſince <hi>you mock God,</hi> we take it the leſs to heart that you <hi>mock us,</hi> for <hi>the Servants are not greater then their Maſters</hi>—of preſenting in a peaceable way their deſires to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> was humbly preſented in our <hi>Repreſentation</hi> and <hi>Petition, Oct.</hi> 5.11. we underſtand with what Spirits, and what were the matters contained therein, and how well they agreed with a peaceable and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſive Spirit: indeed you are very ſubmiſſive men who have taken upon you to <hi>Rule the Nation,</hi> almoſt time out of mind, and I perceive you are very unwilling now to become our Servants, though you do not think it below you to <hi>take the Wages of your hire:</hi> you preſent your <hi>Pelition</hi> very ſubmiſſively, but you reſolve to <hi>have what you ask for</hi>—</p>
            <p>The Genenerall <hi>Councell of Officers</hi> (that is half a ſcore of the <hi>high and mighty Officers,</hi> the reſt being led like a blind man by a Dogg and a Bell) when they agreed the foreſaid <hi>Repreſentation</hi> reſolved then to the end, that the true ſtate of <hi>Affairs</hi> might be communicated to thoſe of the Army who were equally concerned with them <hi>That Copies ſhould be ſent to every Regiment, &amp;c.</hi> inviting them in caſe they were free, to concur with them in their juſt deſires: <hi>See now if this be not a ſubmiſſive way of Petitioning:</hi> for as <hi>Monk</hi> and <hi>Overton</hi> very well write: <hi>If your Repreſentation be already delivered, to what purpoſe is it that we ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe:</hi> to no purpoſe in the world, but knowing that the <hi>Parliament</hi> would never yeild to this unreaſonable Requeſt; they would feel the Pulſe of all the Forces in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> to ſee what numbers they could engage for them, and ſee who would not that they
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119208:11"/> might have an eye upon them, till they could turn them off: and by this means if they could not <hi>fright the Parliament,</hi> yet they could ſorce them out when they <hi>ſaw their time;</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>As ſoon as they had ſetled the Monthly Aſſeſment, and ſurniſhed them with a legall courſe of gathering Money</hi>—</p>
            <p>The <hi>Parliament</hi> upon the Tenth of <hi>October</hi> reſolved, <hi>That the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of the Army had received and ſhould receive from time to time Marks of the Favour of the Parliament, and Countenance anſwerable to their Merit</hi>—A fair Anſwer I think: but it ſeems very far ſhort of what they meant in their firſt <hi>Propoſall;</hi> it is pity but the <hi>Parliament</hi> ſhould be bound to anſwer them to an hair: this is a groſs fault indeed: but it ſeems the next is worſe; <hi>Reſolved, That it is the duty of all perſons, eſpecially Members of Parliament, to inform the Houſe of any thing which in their apprehenſion may concern the publick ſafety; and that it is the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted right of the Parliament to receive and debate thoſe Informations, and reſolve what they think ſit thereupon</hi>—a moſt incomparable generous and truly Engliſh Reſolve; and yet it ſeems being applied to the Armies ſecond Propoſall (never were <hi>Parliament</hi> thus bound to humour a company of <hi>Mercenary Soldiers,</hi> that they muſt have the length of their foot to a hair) it aſſerts that it is the duty of all perſons to inform the Houſe of any thing, be it never ſo frivolous and falſe, and to reſolve thereupon the ruine and deſtruction of perſons and Families: the <hi>Parliament</hi> ſhould have Voted their <hi>Inſormation</hi> frivolous and falſe, and puniſhed the honeſt <hi>Member</hi> that informed them, and then they would never have complained of their <hi>Reſolution: It is a hard matter to pleaſe every fool.</hi>—</p>
            <p>Upon <hi>Tueſday,</hi> the next day after a Bill was brought into the <hi>Houſe,</hi> and contrary to the uſuall Orders of <hi>Parliament,</hi> thrice read in one and the ſame day: this is that <hi>Act</hi> that <hi>cuts them to the heart,</hi> and if it had been read in the <hi>Houſe</hi> two ſeverall daies, you may be ſure an Order would have been taken it ſhould not have been read a third time: <hi>men muſt be quick in caſe of neceſſity;</hi> there was no triſling now, they had found out your Deſign, and it was fit they ſhould <hi>nip you a little?</hi> and you muſt note, <hi>that this was not done before they had notice of this Conſpiracy, of getting hands after the Petition was debated in the Houſe:</hi> There is no reaſon the <hi>Parliament</hi> ſhould take care for them who take ſo little <hi>care for our Parliaments,</hi> but <hi>call them and break them at their pleaſure:</hi> however, <hi>you are not leſt without remedy, Parliaments may give you money when they pleaſe,</hi> and I do not hold it reaſon you ſhould have it any other way: yes, <hi>but by this means the godly Miniſters will ſuffer:</hi> Pray take no care <hi>for that;</hi> you are reſolved to take away their Tithes, and then it matters not much who gets their places:</p>
            <p>Many other miſchiefs you reckon up, but they will fall upon you, own heads; when you foreſaw theſe dangers that would ariſe, what
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119208:11"/> made you ſuch mad men as to break the Parliament; if they had continued, here had been none of all this difficulty; But the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions of your nine <hi>Tories,</hi> or <hi>Bandits</hi> (for ſuch they are having no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions) are a valuable conſideration for all this hazard; yea, this Nation muſt wallow in bloud rather then <hi>Lambert</hi> muſt not be <hi>Lord Lambert:</hi> Could you think the Parliament were ſuch Novices, as to be only your Tools and Engines? we ſhould have laughed at them for their wiſdome, if they had been ſuch Noddies; they had experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of your faithfullneſſe once before:—<hi>Concerning which we adde, That had not ſtrange precipitancy, and deſign driven it on; it could never have been imagined that any Supreme Authority would ever have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed a people to ſuch inconveniencies</hi>—What do you now abuſe them with the Supreme Authority? It ſeems, it was their deſign to be the Supreme Authority, which they could never be while you were the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme power. See how they are at it with Precipitancy again; indeed I think they were too nimble for you; and I am betten pleaſed, you ſhould ſpite them, then pity them; but I think it was your precipitancy that expoſed us to all theſe inconveniencies; and I believe if they had been ten times more, you would have ventured them, rather then part with the Supreme power.—<hi>Things being thus prepared, the next day the Parliament hoping they had a great influence upon part of the Army, and conceiving by their late Acts they had ſufficiently perplexed them, who they doubted might oppoſe them.</hi> (Mark, you ſee by their own confeſſion, thoſe acts were made only in defence;)—<hi>and that the Government of the Nation was ſo ſure in their own hands, as in all probability things muſt run into conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, except managed by themſelves;</hi> as indeed by your own confeſſion they did, after you firſt forced them, till you reſtored them again; &amp; will in all probability ſtill run into diſorder till they are called back to ſettle them; and although you ſcoffe at them, while you tell them they thought the Government ſure in their own hands; yet I think any body that had nor been acquainted with your falſeneſſe, would have thought it had been ſo indeed, when they read in your Papers, <hi>that you were their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, their faithfull ſervants; that you were their Army, that it was your Duty to obey their Commands;</hi> who would have doubted but the Government had been ſure in their hands; till they could have ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Rights of the Nation, and fairly have delivered the power into other hands, by the Sixth of <hi>May</hi> next.</p>
            <p>But if you look back upon your <hi>Declar. May</hi> 6. and <hi>Petition</hi> and <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe,</hi> May 12. you your ſelves give them ſuch high Characters, as one would think they were the fitteſt men to have the Government in their hands. <hi>Reader,</hi> look back, and ponder, I will not repeat.—<hi>In the morning the dores of the Lobby by their appointment being faſt ſhut and guarded, that none might by any means come near the Houſe, or under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand their proceedings,</hi>—And but good reaſon; for you have ſeen
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119208:12"/> before, there are <hi>Tell-tales</hi> Members.—<hi>Occaſion is miniſtred from one of the Letters which was ſigned by ſeverall Officers, according to appointment of the General Council.</hi>—It ſhould ſeem whatever the <hi>Generall Council</hi> Orders muſt be done, Right or Wrong; but 'tis pretty ſport, theſe Signers put the <hi>General Council</hi> upon this work, and then the <hi>General Council</hi> order them to Sign; and the very truth is, a few of them rule the <hi>General Council,</hi> and ſome of their wives rule them, and who do you think Rules the Nation?—<hi>ſent to a Regiment of the Army, and produced by a Member of the Houſe, (it being of no other purpoſe then the ſending of the ſaid Repreſentation to one of the Regiments, as is before mentioned.</hi>—That is to ſay, to get their Subſcriptions, after it had been debated in the Houſe for the ends I mentioned before:—<hi>Nevertheleſſe they fell ſoul upon the ſaid Officers who ſubſcribed it,</hi>—That is very true, and bravely done, for they made no Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of perſons; but fell foul (if you term it ſo) upon every one of them according to the merit of their Confederacy:—<hi>and took this riſe, in purſuance of their former intent, to make a plain breach upon the Army;</hi> the queſtion is, whether they were to be blamed for falling foul upon them without juſt cauſe ſhewn; I appeal to any ſober man. Doth any body think the Parliament ſought any occaſion of breach? did not the Army give them this occaſion? There were <hi>Fifty</hi> Members againſt <hi>Fifteen</hi> in this buſineſſe; and thoſe <hi>Fifteen</hi> had not a word to ſay to excuſe the buſineſſe; but ſome of them were ſilent, as not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what to ſay, or not daring to ſpeak what they thought; and thoſe that ſpake, had no better arguments then this; <hi>the Army could not bear your Rebukes the other day, when you voted againſt a Generall, and how do you think will they bear this?</hi> What is it a plain breach upon the Army to puniſh Treacherous Servants? to <hi>puniſh</hi> them did I ſay? to put them out of <hi>Service:—and thereupon vote out of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, (without hearing, &amp;c.)</hi> This was no time to obſerve Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities; they might have been heard next day if they had pleaſed, but that they had nothing to ſay for themſelves, nor would come at the Parliament, (who upon ſubmiſſion might have made their peace,) or the <hi>General Council</hi> might have repreſented to the Parliament the ſtate of the caſe, if it was miſunderſtood, as ſure enough it was not; elſe they would not have betaken themſelves to their Old Shift of Diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Parliament—<hi>and as they did the other day, they haſtily Now paſſed the Act for the Seven Generalls</hi>—Which had not been done, if <hi>Fleetwood</hi> had not declined being faithfull to the Parliament; but they were rather to take care of <hi>things</hi> then <hi>perſons;</hi> to keep up the Reputation of the Nation, then the Grandeur of the Old Protectors Son-in-law; and therefore if he would be careleſſe of the Intereſt of the Nation, and preferre the Governing of the Nation by the Sword, before the reall Wellfare of ſo many Millions of Souls as were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119208:12"/> in this Affair: The Parliament were not to be blamed, if they put them into command that would be more firm to the Intereſt of the Nation, and into ſo many hands, as might not eaſily agree to enſlave us.—<hi>Whereupon three of the ſaid number (the Houſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journing) immediately repaired to the Speakers Chamber; and having pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided Six Barrels of Powder,</hi> (If this were true, 'twas in their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, ſuſpecting you would force the Houſe; though I have heard ſay you brought them thither, and then gave out, that the other did it) <hi>forthwith gave out Orders for Coll.</hi> Morleys <hi>Regiment to march thither,</hi> (and need enough) <hi>as alſo divers others that they thought would be moſt ſure to them: and likewiſe gave order to</hi> Okey <hi>to draw his Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the</hi> Palace-yard, <hi>upon which he marched to</hi> Tuttle-fields <hi>with Four of his Troops, and from thence having ſent one to the</hi> Palace-yard, <hi>he marched with the other three into</hi> London. Pray mark how exact they are: they tell you where he marched, firſt into <hi>Tuttle-fields,</hi> then ſends one into the <hi>Palace-yard,</hi> himſelf with three more marched into the City: When they tell truth, you have the exact time, place, number, every circumſtance that you may trace it to a tack: But as I noted before, when they juggle, there is no ſuch exactneſs, if many things before recited had been true, you ſhould have been ſure to have had then every circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to a tittle; being hardly of leſſe conſideration, and more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of our knowledge, then that Coll. <hi>Okey</hi> marched into <hi>Tuttle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fields;</hi>—he marched into <hi>London,</hi> for countenancing the draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together the <hi>Militia</hi> Forces in order to a conjunction with him (and may his Poſterity be your Vaſſals, that might have done it, and did not) it might have ſaved what we may now pay more dearly for;—<hi>But this had better ſucceſſe in</hi> Southwark, <hi>where</hi> Thomſons <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment drew together;</hi> and indeed they are highly to be honoured for the only <hi>Engliſh Spirits</hi> within the <hi>Lines of Communication;</hi> it was time for the Parliament to look about them.</p>
            <p>—<hi>The Officers of the Army having received notice of theſe things thereupon judged it their duty to draw together in Arms; and march to the</hi> Palace-yard, <hi>the place they had appointed for their Rendezvouze;</hi> that was the place of their Rendezvouze formerly upon the like occaſion;—<hi>to underſtand the grounds of their ſo aſſembling themſelves together;</hi> and does any body think this was all the buſineſſe? no ſure 'twas for no good that this was their place of Rendezvouze; the Parliament knew their old tricks, and where to expect them the next morning; they do not tell us what time of the night or day it was, when they came to the <hi>Palace-yard,</hi> nor when they came to the <hi>Lord Maiors;</hi> but Captain <hi>Pride</hi> can tell you who met them in the way. One would think as they tell the ſtory, that <hi>Okey</hi> had been in the City before them; and that <hi>Thompſons</hi> men were up before they thought of Arming them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves;</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:119208:13"/>
            <p>—<hi>And being arrived there, and finding ſeverall Companyes of</hi> Morleyes <hi>Regiment were placed in the Hall,</hi> (whom it ſhould ſeem you did not expect to finde there, falling into their power before you were well aware, who might have ſpoiled you, if they had intended any thing more then to defend their Maſters <hi>the Parliament,</hi> whom you came to force from their truſt)—<hi>and for the grounds and reaſons aforemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned (as alſo that they might not be encouraged in ſuch a dangerous oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, to the apparent hazard of the publick peace,)</hi> There needed have been no oppoſition nor breach of peace if you had not made it; your Fellow-Soldiers intended only to guard the Parliament, as in all duty and conſcience they were bound—therefore upon you be the breach whatever yet may happen:—<hi>We found our ſelves neceſſitated to put a period and determination to the Parliaments meeting together.</hi> Your ever Renowned Generall taught you this prank, you are very towardly Babes of Grace.</p>
            <p>—<hi>And think our ſelves yet further obliged</hi> (ſure you do but think ſo) <hi>to declare all Orders, Acts, pretended Acts, or other Declarations, or any of them, made, enacted or paſs'd on Monday the</hi> 10 <hi>of</hi> October, <hi>and on Tueſday and Wedneſday following, them and every of them null and void, to all intents and purpoſes;</hi> (this would do very well, if it were ſo eaſily done) <hi>and do hereby declare them and every of them, and every Clauſe and ſentence of them, invalid, null and void to all intents and purpoſes; and likewiſe all Acts and Orders and proceedings thereupon had or done, in as full and ample manner, at if the ſaid Orders, Acts, pretended Acts, or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations, and every of them had never been done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Very gallant, and I Declare you and every of you, ſtark mad, in as full and ample manner, as if you were of the Congregation of <hi>Bedlam;</hi> or as any there are, to all intents and purpoſes.</p>
            <p>—<hi>All which we thought fit to publiſh, hoping all unprejudiced perſons will acquieſce in the juſtice and neceſſity hereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I do not know what you hope, but I dare ſay, no unbyaſſed ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional man can either approve the juſtice, or dare juſtifie the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity thereof; upon my conſcience you can no more juſtifie this action before indifferent judges, then I can, if I ſhould break open my neighbours houſe, and rob his cheſt.</p>
            <p>Reader, I leave thee free to judge, you have ſeen what the Army ſay for themſelves, and how double tongued they are; you have ſeen them compared with their former ſelves, and how unlike them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves they look. You have ſeen what they have ſaid againſt the <hi>Honourable Parliament,</hi> or any members thereof, which is ſo far from any miſcarriages, that they have done the Parliament this kindneſs, to let the Nation ſee a little how much they are indebted to them and generally men are well aſſured that the Parliament meant the Nation a very happy Government, in the enjoyment of their
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119208:13"/> ancient <hi>Birth-rights:</hi> and who ever he be that can ſhew us wherein they have broke their <hi>Truſt</hi> repoſed in them in the leaſt, ſince they ſate, <hi>Let him caſt the firſt ſtone at them:</hi> and I will ſtand ſtill and hold my peace; they would have been ſure to heare of it in this <hi>Declaration,</hi> if any ſuch thing had been true: and let me tell you here <hi>(which I forgot before, for all what the Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſayth) That the Parliament in the Act before mentioned, did expreſly take care of the Act of Oblivion, and the Adventurers for Lands in</hi> Ireland, <hi>excepting them particularly in the ſaid Act, that nothing in the ſayd Act ſhould be conſtrued to the Impairing thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will onely now rightly ſtate the Caſe between the <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>Army</hi> very briefly and impartially, becauſe you have ſeen how the <hi>Army</hi> faulter and mince the matter.—</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Army having made a Rod for their own Breach, by agreeing to the Protectors nominating his Succeſſor (as they had agreed him to be King, if he had lived a little longer) the old Man dying, up ſtarts his Son to Reign in his stead (whom God made an honeſter man then his Father) the Army ſoon finding him too carefull of the Liberties of</hi> England <hi>(though Principled for Kingſhip: an Epide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micall Diſeaſe among them at that time) they were deſirous to have</hi> Fleetwood <hi>their Generall (fearing elſe their Kingdome would not laſt long) but the</hi> Protector <hi>was perſwaded it was better for him to be Generall, and let</hi> Fleetwood <hi>be</hi> Protector (I think ſo too) but if a Generall, he was as willing to truſt <hi>Falconbridge,</hi> as <hi>Fleet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood.</hi>—</p>
            <p>In this Juncture of Affairs, the <hi>Protector</hi> haſtens a <hi>Parliament,</hi> as they called it; which though it was thwacked with <hi>Officers</hi> of the <hi>Army</hi> and many <hi>Penſioners</hi> of his <hi>Highneſs,</hi> yet could not endure to be Bearded by <hi>Wallingſord houſe,</hi> nor will any <hi>Parliament</hi> ever e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ure it till the Worlds end.</p>
            <p>Hereupon followed thoſe Votes for the diſcontinuing their Generall Councels: which put them in ſuch a Rage, that nothing would ſerve them but its Diſſolution, which accordingly was effected: now all the Power falls into the hands of <hi>Wallingford-houſe,</hi> who had many thoughts of heart, and Conſultations how to ſettle the Nation in the way they are now agoing; merning nothing leſs in the World, then the recalling this <hi>Parliament:</hi> but ſo it fell out, that ſome honeſt Hearts ſet this Deſign a going among them, which took ſo with the ſmall <hi>Officers</hi> of a ſudden, that there was no way (though enough againſt the mindes of ſome <hi>Grandees</hi>) but this <hi>Parliament muſt be called.</hi> The Great men ſeeing things thus run againſt them, and their Intereſts were forced to each hold of this <hi>Twig</hi> to ſave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from drowning <hi>(as they now tell us, with is the trueſt word in all their Declaration)</hi> to keep their Heads above water: To
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119208:14"/> this end they had the previous Meetings with ſome leading Members, <hi>(as they call them)</hi> to Cog them into a ſubſerviency of their Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt; and hoping well that this <hi>Twig might keep their Intereſt from ſinking a while:</hi> They moſt Chriſtian like diſſemble their Repentance in their <hi>Declaration, May</hi> 6. and invite the <hi>Parliament to return:</hi> but 'tis well known, <hi>they did but lye in their hearts, when they took ſhame to themſelves:</hi> unleſs they were convinced, and converted in the very minute of penning that <hi>Declaration.</hi> the <hi>Parliament</hi> being Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled, it was ſoon manifeſt by their Addreſs of <hi>May</hi> 12. what De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes they drove at, Viz. <hi>A Senate to check the Parliament,</hi> and Eight and twenty thouſand pounds <hi>per annum</hi> for the <hi>Protector</hi> and his <hi>Mother,</hi> and to have <hi>Fleetwood Commander in chief,</hi> of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> to ſay nothing of the Two latter: The Honeſty of the <hi>Parliament</hi> is for ever to be had in Memory, that they did not agree for a <hi>Senate:</hi> ſuch a Temptation as hath hardly ever been reſiſted by men: for by this means moſt, or all of the <hi>Parliament</hi> might have been joyned with the Ringleaders of the <hi>Army,</hi> and been a <hi>Senate</hi> for ever; called <hi>Parliaments</hi> and made Fools of them, having no Power left them to do any thing but by concurrence of the <hi>Senate:</hi> thus they might have been an <hi>Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Parliament,</hi> and they and their good Servants have ruled for ever and ever: this Propoſition of the Army not being anſwered to their Expectation; for this was the main of the matter—together with their <hi>receiving Commiſſions from the Parliament,</hi> which was put upon them, <hi>to oblige their Conſciences to that duty, which they declared they owed unto the Parliament:</hi> the <hi>Parliament</hi> finding them not altogether ſuch humble Servants as they declared themſelves; which <hi>Commiſſions</hi> they accepted for Peace ſake, till they ſhould finde an <hi>opportunity to turn over a new leaf:</hi> Much regret was diſcovered againſt this by many <hi>Principall Blades,</hi> and many thoughts of heart there were, how to <hi>get their Necks out of this Yoke,</hi> that they might the better go on for a <hi>Senate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the mean time Sir <hi>George Booth's</hi> Rebellion breaks out, which being quelled, ſome of the <hi>Officers of that Brigade</hi> (for you muſt believe <hi>Lambert</hi> had no hand in it) found it upon their hearts to <hi>conſult how they might improve this for the Glory of God</hi> (you know what I mean) then up comes this Paper for a Generall, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>Officers,</hi> the onely means to effect their <hi>Deſigns:</hi> but this <hi>(with it may be ſome other particulars)</hi> were too groſs: and had been grievouſly rebuked by the <hi>Parliament:</hi> However this <hi>Deſign</hi> muſt not be layd aſide <hi>(for their Good old Cauſe would down if it did)</hi> although <hi>Fleetwood</hi> had undertook great Matters to the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> to ſtill this <hi>noiſe of the Waters, and tumult of his People.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:119208:14"/>
            <p>But after long Banding among the <hi>Generall Councell,</hi> and <hi>rancor enough againſt the Parliament;</hi> to the <hi>Parliament they came with a Petition and Repreſentations,</hi> full of <hi>ſweet Expreſſions</hi> of <hi>Obedience and Duty</hi> (to have drill'd out the <hi>Act</hi> of 100000 <hi>l. per menſem,</hi> and the <hi>Cuſtonics and Exciſe,</hi> which was well enough underſtood) but their <hi>Repreſentation</hi> abuſing the <hi>Information</hi> the <hi>Houſe had received,</hi> and their <hi>Petition</hi> calling for ſome things of <hi>dangerous conſequence,</hi> they could not then receive an Anſwer thereunto, but had the <hi>thanks of the Houſe for the good Expreſſions of their Affections.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the mean while it muſt not ſleep, but the ſaid <hi>Petition</hi> muſt be diſpatched to every <hi>Regiment</hi> and <hi>Garriſon,</hi> as was ſaid before: the <hi>Parliament</hi> in the mean while go on to conſider their <hi>Petition,</hi> and reſolve very honourably upon <hi>ſeverall heads thereof:</hi> during this <hi>Jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture,</hi> the <hi>Parliament</hi> having certain aſſurance of the ſaid <hi>Conſpiracy</hi> of going about to engage all the <hi>Forces</hi> of this <hi>Common-wealth</hi> to ſide with them in their ſaid unreaſonable <hi>Deſires,</hi> and a Letter being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced with the <hi>Names of ſeverall Officers,</hi> wherein was incloſed one of the ſaid <hi>Petitions</hi> to be ſubſcribed by the <hi>Regiment, to whom it was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Parliament</hi> alſo taking notice of the <hi>miſchievouſneſs of their Deſire, That no Officer might be Disbanded but by a Court Martiall;</hi> whereby they would have been enabled to Caſhire any <hi>Officer</hi> that was faithful to his <hi>Truſt,</hi> they having no other way to ſuppreſs that <hi>Conſcience</hi> that was in many <hi>Commanders, That they ought to be faithfull to them from whom they had received their Commiſſions:</hi> Nor had they any other way to carry on their <hi>Deſign of a Senate,</hi> the moſt horrid Vilany that ever was mentioned among us; and there being no other Conſtruction to be made of it, <hi>but the Army by doing thus after their Petition was delivered, and Debated, intended to force their Deſires; their faithfull Servants going about to play</hi> REX, <hi>the Parliament could not but finde it a Duty highly incumbent on them, if they would be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the Intereſt of their Country, to uſe their beſt Endeavours to ſtop this Carrier.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hereupon it was (with good reaſon) reſolved, <hi>That no Money ſhould be levied upon the people of</hi> England, <hi>without their conſent in Parliament, and other things in that Act contained, of very great prudence to the end forementioned: and then with much Juſtice diſcharged the ſaid Officers, who had ſigned the ſaid Letter from their Imployments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Parliament</hi> knowing how well ſome of the Army ſtood affected to them, and how this would ripen and whet that violence that would nevertheleſs ſhortly have been acted upon them, hoped well that <hi>Fleetwood</hi> would have been faithfull to his Truſt—(whoſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mſſion was altogether, or very neer of as long continuance as the <hi>Parliament</hi> had reſolved the uttermoſt of their Seſſion, <hi>Viz.</hi> (till
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119208:15"/> 
               <hi>May</hi> next) but he then loſt that Reputation of Faithfulneſs which he had with many men before, and declined the ſecuring of the <hi>Parliaments</hi> Priviledges, and after acted againſt them; <hi>Of which I hope he will repent one day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Parliament being at this loſs,</hi> Created ſeven Commiſſioners, (of which nevertheleſs he was one) but this was below him <hi>forſooth;</hi> Three whereof began to act for Guarding the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> expecting that a Force ſhould be put upon the <hi>Houſe,</hi> which was ſoon endeavoured; for it was not long before a conſiderable Party came into the <hi>Palace Yard</hi> for the ſame purpoſe: but being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented of taking poſſeſſion of the <hi>Houſe,</hi> they intercepted the Speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, and after Affronts given him, turned him back: and ſo they ſay they have put a period to the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I appeal whether this be the naked ſtate of the Caſe, and truth of the Matter yea or no to their own Conſciences.</p>
            <p>You will judge then, they have well told thir own Tale; the reſt of the ſtory every body knows; and I haſten to the Preſs.—</p>
            <p>It remains now, that I ſhould make ſome Obſervations upon what, they declare, is upon their hearts to do, but becauſe what is upon their hearts to day, or what they tell us is upon their hearts to day, will be at their Heels to Morrow.</p>
            <p>I hold it not at all worth my Labour, but reſolve henceforward never ot believe what they declare for the Good of the Nation, till I ſee it done, and then I ſhall never believe it: and for what they reſolve to do, which tends onely to <hi>Ruine,</hi> as ſome things they now have upon their <hi>Hearts;</hi> look <hi>ſturvily</hi> that way. I ſhall heartily wiſh that ſome wiſer men may take the WORK out of their Hands: Or if I ſhould take them a little to Task, I ſhould but make ſport, and I am loth to be a Foole in the Play: Doth any body think that they will endeavour that a (Due) I do not underſtand what they mean by that Word <hi>Due;</hi> I doubt it comes from a Root that ſignifies <hi>ſomething elſe beſides Juſt</hi>) Liberty may be aſſured to all the Free-born People of theſe Nations: Free-born People of the Nations, who are they? they muſt be twenty years old and upwards I think, but if they were not born Fooles, I am ſure they are made Fooles, what pretty Work are they like to make with the Reformation of the <hi>LAW?</hi> ſure no body doubts but you will do more <hi>hurt</hi> then <hi>good</hi>—</p>
            <p>That a faithful, godly, and painful Goſpel Preaching Miniſtry may be maintained; a long ſtory, but not a word of Learning, no that is ſuperſtitious He warrant you: they can tell you the minde of <hi>Chriſt</hi> peremptorily enough, without conſulting the Originall: not a <hi>Wiſe man among them at their Devotions in Whitehall:</hi> And the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119208:15"/> truth is, if they would make <hi>all of our Miniſters Officers of the Army,</hi> they might be maintained in a more certain and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable way, <hi>then that ſcurvy way of Tythes;</hi> which will yet be more vexatious to the People ten thouſand times, <hi>when you can bring it into the Exchequer,</hi> as I really believe <hi>that to be the Deſign.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here comes a moſt certain Truth, no body queſtions it, <hi>Why do you trouble your ſelves about it? We have no Aimes or Ends to ſet up a Military, or Arbitrary Power</hi>—but I hope Neceſſity may put you upon it, if the People prove unruly, and will not ſubmit to <hi>thoſe Principles you have agreed among your ſelves</hi>—But have already provided <hi>(you ſhall have no thanks for your paine)</hi> that the Civill and Executive part of Government may be lodged in a <hi>Committee of Safety:</hi> This is a fine <hi>new Name</hi> indeed; this is no <hi>Military Government:</hi> Whoſe <hi>Deputies</hi> are they trow, if one ſhould Carechiſe them?</p>
            <list>
               <item>Queſtion, <hi>Who made you?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Anſwer,</hi> The Generall Councell of <hi>Officers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Queſt. <hi>Who gave you your Name?</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Generall Councell of <hi>Officers.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>How many <hi>Colonels, Generals,</hi> and <hi>Lords</hi> of the <hi>Army</hi> are there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them? what are they no <hi>Military Power,</hi> becauſe they are not all of the <hi>Generall Councell of Officers?</hi> yet there is one Lawyer among them, it ſeems, and that makes them a <hi>Civill Power,</hi> I think half of this <hi>Committee of Safety,</hi> are of the <hi>Generall Councell of Officers;</hi> and yet they have no Aimes to ſet up a <hi>Military Power</hi>—and they obliged in a ſhort time <hi>(I thought it bad been juſt ſix weeks)</hi> to prepare ſuch a form of Government, as may beſt ſute with a <hi>Free State and Common-wealth:</hi> that is wiſely done He promiſe you; I hope they have more wit then to be obliged to it: can you tell what <hi>is that form that will beſt ſute?</hi> or will you take their words for it, <hi>That what they prepare is the beſt?</hi> if they ſhould have ſo good a conceit of their own Contrivances, <hi>as to promiſe you that it is ſuch?</hi> No, <hi>It muſt be according to the Principles agreed upon at</hi> Wallingford <hi>Houſe, muſt it not?</hi> wherein, no doubt <hi>all that know you,</hi> will ſay on your behalfs, <hi>You are not ſufficient for theſe things:</hi> and will cry unto the Lord <hi>(not to carry on the work in your hands)</hi> no ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men dare do that; <hi>That he will ariſe from his holy Habitation, and judge the Cauſe of the oppreſſed, of the Father leſs, and the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow: That he would judge between them that fear God, and them that fear him not: That he would make bare his holy Arme, and witneſs againſt the ungodlineſs and unrighteouſneſs of them, even thoſe that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119208:16"/> have made void his Law. That he would ſcatter the people that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in War; And that they that take the Sword, may periſh by the Sword: And that he would reſtore us Judges as at the firſt, and Counſellors as at the beginning; Men fearing God and hating Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: To be Repairers of our breaches, and Reſtorers of Paths for us to dwell in: That we may never want</hi> Parliaments <hi>to Rule over us: leaſt we become a Prey to the Teeth of unreaſonable men, whoſe tender mercies are cruelties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for you, Soldiers, that you may do no Violence, but be content with your Wages; and if for this we become your Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and you count us evill men, becauſe we cannot ſay as you ſay: <hi>Let God, the righteous God, judge between</hi> US, <hi>and</hi> YOU.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:119208:16"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>REader,</hi> Take notice there is two ſheets of Paper, Intituled, <hi>A Parliamenters Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition to the Army:</hi> which is <hi>verbatim</hi> the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part of a late Book, Intituled, <hi>The Grand Concernments of England Enſured:</hi> To which ſome body hath added one Page of Notes, ſtoln out of a <hi>Sermon,</hi> which I utterly diſown and diſlike. All which is done without any knowledge of mine, and I fear with no good deſign:—Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides ſome expreſsions of thoſe prophetick Notes (as they are ſtyled) were ſeverely cenſured by learned, and godly men, as ſavouring of too much Levity, and for his <hi>Sermon,</hi> I think the Parliament gave him no thanks.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
